Guide to the Japanese medical manuscript notebooks, 1810-1849 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Japanese medical manuscript notebooks 1810-1849 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
3.5 Linear Feet 63 Items
The sixty-three manuscript volumes in this collection range from 10 to 154 pages, and were created in Japan from about 1810 to 1849, chiefly by medical students. The notebooks usually take one of two forms: transcriptions of lectures and demonstrations, and bodies of knowledge written up as manuals by well-known Japanese physicians of the time, especially Hanaoka Seishū and Takenaka Bunpō. Topics covered include herbal medicines and other prescriptions; treatments for diseases of the eyes and other parts of the head; surgery, particularly for cancers, tumors, and fistulas; breast cancer; smallpox; scurvy; osteopathy; treatment of wounds; suturing; hematology; gynecology and obstetrics; and pediatric medicine.
Some notebooks contain black-and-white and color hand-drawn illustrations - many full-page - of surgeries, close-ups of suturing, bandages and wrappings, osteopathic manipulations, and medicinal plants. In most cases, the author or copyist recorded details such the place and time of the lecture and the name of the medical school. There are references in the notes to at least a dozen other contemporary or earlier physicians, and to earlier dates for the work being copied - these range from 1677 to 1796. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Japanese medical manuscript notebooks collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2012.
Historical and Biographical Note
At the time when these volumes were written in the first quarter of the 19th century, Japanese medical practice was quite advanced due to a melding of Chinese, Portuguese, and Dutch medical practices, and the pioneering advances of Japanese physicians. By the early 1800s there were a number of medical schools in Japan, two of which are mentioned in the notebooks: Shunrinken (春 林 軒), Hanaoka Seishū's medical school located in Wakayama prefecture; and Seibidō (済 美 堂), located in Kyōto, led by Takenaka Bunpō. Some of the early medical schools such as Shunrinken graduated hundreds of medical students within a short period. Copying lecture notes and materia medica was part of the learning process, and resulted in a kind of manuscript medical manual that was then used for further studies or copied and passed down to other students. Several of the notebooks in this collection refer to bodies of knowledge originally authored by Hanaoka Seishū and Takenaka Bunpō.
Hanaoka Seishū (華 岡 青 洲) (1760-1835) was most known for his study and teaching of herbal medicine, surgical techniques, and the treatment of cancers, fistulas, and other serious ailments; he was also well-known for his pioneering use of general anesthesia long before it was first attempted by Western physicians. He advocated for the adoption of Western medicine as practiced by Dutch physicians, allying it with traditional Japanese Kampo medicine, which focused on herbal and mineral preparations.
Takenaka Bunpō (竹 中 文 輔) (1766-1836), also known as Takenaka Bisai and Takenaka Nanpō, studied in Kyoto under Wada Tōkaku and specialized in surgical techniques and smallpox treatments.
Collection Overview
The sixty-three Japanese manuscript volumes in this collection were created from 1810 to 1849, chiefly by medical students, and document Japanese medical training and practice during the time also known as the Edo period, and the conjoining of Chinese-inspired materia medica with current Western medical practices introduced primarily by the Dutch. The notebooks range in length from 10 to 154 pages, and typically take the form of transcriptions of lectures and demonstrations; in many cases the writer recorded the place and time of the demonstration and the name of the medical school. There are also volumes which represent the collected knowledge of well-known Japanese physicians of the time, especially Hanaoka Seishū but also Takenaka Bunsuke (Nanpō). There are references in the notes to at least a dozen other contemporary or earlier physicians.
The copyists and note-takers signed their names at the end of the volumes; the name Yamanaka Shūsai Hideyuki appears most frequently; also appearing frequently are the names of editors and proofreaders, and corrections and later annotations in red ink are found in a number of the manuscripts. In addition to the contemporary dates, there are many references to the earlier manuscript versions being copied: these dates range from 1677 to 1796.
The topics covered by the volumes range widely, and include: herbal medicine and other prescriptions; treatments for diseases of the eye and other parts of the head; surgery, particularly on cancers, swellings, and fistulas; breast cancer; smallpox; scurvy; osteopathy; the treatment of wounds; hematology; gynecology and obstetrics; and pediatric medicine. There are several volumes containing illustrative drawings, some hand-colored and others are black-and-white; they include detailed images of surgical procedures and close-ups of suturing; examples of bandages and wrappings; osteopathic manipulations; and medicinal plants.
One volume in particular stands out above the rest, consisting of over ninety carefully drawn, full-page, hand-coloured illustrations, nine of which are double-page, displaying patients with dislocated limbs, skin cancer, or requiring sophisticated bandages, as well as illustrations of internal organs and one page with surgical instruments. One of the illustrations is a realistic portrait of Hanaoka Seishū, with a beard and spectacles (probably imported from Holland), showing him excising a cyst from a patient. At the end of the volume, two different explanatory texts in Kanbun (classical Chinese read in the Japanese manner) provide comments in the volume about the diseases and their treatment.
Each codex in the collection is composed of leaves of rice paper, with hand-sewn bindings and soft covers, and calligraphy in black and red ink. Some of the texts are written in Shino Japanese (Chinese reading style) using all Kanji characters, while other texts are in Shino Japanese written in 19th-century characters - the language of the educated class in Japan. At least one volume (Vol. 21) contains Dutch words for medicinal compounds. The script reads back to front; the script is laid out in vertical columns that are read from right to left across the page. In some cases, pages or sections and covers are missing, and some volumes bear traces of insect damage, but for the most part, the volumes are remarkably well-preserved.
All titles are taken when possible from the covers or from section headings; approximate translations in English provided by library staff and are in brackets. In the case of missing titles, a title was supplied from content by library staff. Titles and significant names are also given in Japanese characters, and some older calendar dates are also given in modern Western dates. Illegible or untranslatable text is indicated by blank lines.
Volumes are arranged in this collection guide in two series: sets of notebooks, and single volumes. The items in the sets are linked by common themes or bodies of knowledge, and range from two to eleven volumes. They include collections of works by one physician, as well as sets of manuals and lecture notes on topics such as obstetrics and gynecology, metallurgy, opthalmology, pox and skin diseases, and others. Single volumes are housed after the sets.
All titles are taken when possible from the covers or from section headings; approximate translations in English provided by library staff and are in brackets. Titles and significant names are also given in Japanese characters.
Each volume has been assigned a unique institutional identifier.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Hanaoka, Seishū, 1760-1835
華岡青洲, 1760-1835
Takenaka, Nanpō, 1766-1836
竹中南峯, 1766-1836
Yamanaka Shūsai Hideyuki
山中秀斎秀之
Anesthesiology -- History
Breast -- Cancer -- Surgery -- Japan
Eye -- Diseases
Gynecology -- Japan -- History
Hematology -- History
Herbs -- Therapeutic use -- Japan -- History
Internal medicine -- Japan -- History
Medical colleges -- Japan
Medical illustration -- History
Medical students -- Japan -- History
Medicine -- Japan -- History
Medicine -- Japan -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.
Medicine -- Japan -- Manuscripts
Medicine -- Study and teaching -- Japan -- Edo period, 1600-1868
Ophthalmology -- History
Pediatrics -- Japan -- History
Pharmacology -- Japan -- History
Physicians -- Japan -- History
Osteopathic medicine -- History
Smallpox
Surgery -- Japan -- History
Japan -- History -- 1787-1868
History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Related Material
Notes from lectures of Seishū Hanaoka, circa 1802-1806 (manuscript volume)
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Multi-Volume Sets, (37 volumes)
  The notebooks gathered in sets are linked by common themes or bodies of knowledge, and range from two to eleven volumes. They include collections of works by one physician, as well as sets of manuals and lecture notes on topics such as obstetrics and gynecology, metallurgy, opthalmology, pox and skin diseases, and others. Single volumes are listed after the multi-volume sets.
  All titles are taken when possible from the covers or from section headings; approximate translations in English provided by library staff and are in brackets. Titles and significant names are also given in Japanese characters. Each volume has been assigned a unique institutional identifier.
  - Hōdoku benkai / 方読弁解 一, undated
    This set of five notebooks is a copy of one of Dr. Futei Fukui's most famous works, a guide to medicinal compounds containing herbs and minerals for various illnesses: neuralgia, gout, beriberi, stitch, gonorrheal infection, intestinal torsion, and others. All the notebooks contain an index. Volumes 3 and 4 have extensive insect damage. Fukui was a doctor in Kyoto but he was called to Edo by the shogunate in 1790.
    - Hōdoku benkai, Vol. 1 / 方読弁解 一 (Box 1, Volume RL_100050_V_01)
    - Hōdoku benkai, Vol. 2 / 方読弁解 一 (Box 1, Volume RL_100050_V_02)
    - Hōdoku benkai, Vol. 3 / 方読弁解 一 (Box 1, Volume RL_100050_V_03)
    - Hōdoku benkai, Vol. 4 / 方読弁解 一 (Box 1, Volume RL_100050_V_04)
    - Hōdoku benkai, Vol. 5 / 方読弁解 一 (Box 1, Volume RL_100050_V_05)
  - Seibidō hōmoku / 済美堂方目, undated, (2 volumes)
    These two large manuscript notebooks are each 93 pages long and their content is the same. Both volumes contain guidelines for making medicinal compounds in the form of pills and powders. There is a 16-page index which lists medicinal compounds for various illnesses. Both volumes are missing their covers. Seibidō / 済美堂 is the name of a medical practice of Dr. Takenaka Bunpō (1766-1836) / 竹中文輔, a doctor in Kyoto, who studied surgery and smallpox treatment.
    - Seibidō hōmoku / 済美堂方目 (Box 1, Volume RL_100050_V_06)
    - Seibidō hōmoku / 済美堂方目 (Box 1, Volume RL_100050_V_07)
  - Seibidō gansan hō / 済美堂丸散方, 1829, 1848, (2 volumes)
    Both volumes also contain guidelines for making medicinal compounds in the form of pills and powders. At the end of the first notebook, there is a signature, probably of a medical student, Yamanaka Hideyuki / 山中秀之, dated Kōka tsuchinoe saru [1848], March. At 71 pages, the first volume covers more ground than the smaller one, which has 37 pages, but the contents are very similar. The second volume bears this note: "Bunsei 12 [1829] April by Yamanaka Hideyuki / 山中秀之 at Seibidō juku [a medical school]."
    - Seibidō hōmoku / 済美堂方目 (Box 1, Volume RL_100050_V_08)
    - Seibidō hōmoku / 済美堂方目 (Box 1, Volume RL_100050_V_09)
  - Shunrinken ke shaku / 春林軒家 尺の中に日, 1827-1828, (7 volumes)
    This set of manuscript notebooks (six plus a related volume) contains lectures by Hanaoka Seishū / 華岡青洲, and may have additional sections related to other physicians or medical lecturers. Shunrinken is the name of the medical school whose founding physician was Seishū.
    - Gansan hō tsuki kōhō [Pills and powder medicines plus ointments], Vol. 1 / 丸散方附膏方, 1827 (Box 2, Volume RL_100050_V_11)
      Contains receipts for medicinal pills and powders from pages 1-44. A section on ointments follows, with the page numbers starting anew from 1-30. Date: "Bunsei 10 [1827], July at Seibidōjuku; recorded by Yamanaka Shūsai Hideyuki" / 山中周斎秀之.
    - Shohō binran [Prescription manual], Vol. 2 / 処方便覧, 1828 (Box 2, Volume RL_100050_V_12)
      Contains two sections: one is a collection of receipts for medicines, "copied by Sen Chōsai / 宣暢斎 in Bunsei tsuchinoe ne [1828], August 28 to 30 at Dr. Seishū's shinjuku /新塾 [new school]." The title of the second part, Tōshin bassui / 痘疹抜粋, relates to smallpox, discussing diagnostic techniques, treatment methods, and prescription compounds. "Copied in Bunsei 11 nen tsuchinoe ne [1828], August 19-20 at Dr. Seishū shinjuku [new school] by Shūhin / 鷲瀕."
    - [Untitled], Vol. 3, 1827 (Box 2, Volume RL_100050_V_13)
      This volume is divided into five sections, each with its own title. The sections consist of lectures by Hanaoka Seishū and possibly other individuals; topics include case studies of various kinds, breast cancer, and scurvy. Most of the lectures seem to have taken place in late July 1827. In all cases, the writer adds his name to the text.
      Section 1: Nyūgan shin [Breast cancer]. Includes case studies. 1827 July 22-25, written by Yamanaka Shūsai.
      Section 2: Tenkei hiroku: lectures by Dr. Seishū, notes taken by Sen Chōsai / 宣暢斎, 1827 July 27.
      Section 3: Chōsō shin mei: lectures by Dr. Seishū, notes taken by Yamanaka Hideyuki, 1827 July 25-26.
      Section 4: Rishitsu sagen: lecture presented by Dr. Seishū, notes taken by Sen Chōsai, edited by Watanabe Shōmei / 渡辺昭明, 1827 July 28-29.
      Section 5: Kakke Yokuhō: notes on scurvy taken by Sen Chōsai, 1827 July 28-29.
    - [Untitled], Vol. 4, 1828 (Box 2, Volume RL_100050_V_14)
      A notebook divided into five sections, each with its own title. They appear to be medical lectures given at the Shunrinken school.
      Section 1: Gansan hōkō [Pills and powder medicines] Preface written by Hanaoka, Shinpaku / 華岡震伯 Original content was from 1790. The text is written in Kanbun style (Shino/Japanese style writing), with the main sections written in regular Japanese. Gives name of medicine, then short description of which illnesses it is used for, followed by how it should be prescribed. Written by Shūhin in December 1828 at Shunrinken shin juku.
      Section 2: Seishū sensei shinzetsu yōketsu [Summary of Dr. Seishū's medical examination of the tongue] Lecture notes taken originally by student Mitsumura Hyakubai Shigekimi. Dated 1828 February, copied by Sen Chōsai at Shunrinken shin juku.
      Section 3: Seishū sensei sanjutsu tsuke keiken [Dr. Seishū's experience on three herbal medicines.] Written 1828 July 2-21, by Sen Chōsai at Shunrinken shin juku.
      Section 4: Seishū sensei chiken [Dr. Seishū's treatments and examinations] Contains case studies, such as a child with a burn injury that resulted in three adhered fingers. Some of the case studies include patient names and where the patients were from. Dated 1828 August 17-18, written by Shūhin / 鷲瀕.
      Section 5: Seishū sensei chiken furoku kōyaku [Dr. Seishū's treatments and examinations] Supplement to Section 4. Includes five case studies on various operations and treatments. Written in December 1828 by Shūhin at Shunrinken. Some small illustrations of treatments for polydactylism and cutaneous syndactyly are included in this section.
    - Seishū sensei idan, Vol. 5 / 青洲先生医談, 1828 (Box 2, Volume RL_100050_V_15)
      This notebook contains medical lectures on various illnesses and surgical and suturing techniques.
      Section 1: Seishū sensei idan [Medical case studies of Dr. Seishū] Covers breast cancer, swellings and growths on the body, surgical methods, tetanus, anal fistula, and syphilis. Small illustrations are embedded in the texts. August 5-14 1828, Sen Chōsai.
      Section 2: Saidan hen: Surgical techniques for many of the diseases listed in previous section. August 14-16, 1828 Sen Chōsai.
      Section 3: Rokujō sensei idan: Dr. Rokujō's medical lecture. Covers phimotic penis and its treatment, buboes, and various other diseases. Written July 3-5, 1828 by Sen Chōsai.
      Section 4: Rokujō sensei chihō tekiyō: Summary of Dr. Rokujō's remarks on treatment for piles, gonorrheal urethritis. Written July 31-August 2, 1828 by Shūhin.
      Dr. Rokujō is a younger brother of Hanaoka Seishū.
    - Tōkaku Wada sensei idan Seishū Hanaoka sensei hyō [Dr. Wada's medical talk and comments from Dr. Seishū], Vol. 6 / 東郭和田先生医談 青洲華岡先生評, 1828 (Box 2, Volume RL_100050_V_16)
      Written in Bunsei 11 [1828] December by Sen Chōsai. Several medical cases are discussed.
      Dr. Wada Tōkaku (和田東郭) (1744-1803) became a medical officer of the Imperial Court in 1797.
    - Wada Tōkaku sensei idan Hanaoka Seishū sensei hyō [Dr. Wada's medical talk and comment from Dr. Seishū] Zen / 和田東郭先生医談 華岡青洲先生評 全, 1845 (Box 2, Volume RL_100050_V_17)
      Written by Kōka 2 [1845] Shōgatsu [January], Kokubo Indō [or Toradō?] This notebook, although not part of the previous group, features almost the same content as RL_100050_V_16 as well as the same title, but was copied in 1845 rather than 1828.
  - Medical manuals on obstetrics and gynecology, (11 volumes)
    This group of manuals covers many topics related to obstetrics and gynecology: childbirth techniques, surgical methods, diagnostic techniques, and female diseases and treatments. The content includes case studies. Most of the notebooks have tables of contents, and most have titles. The group begins with a set of five notebooks, followed by several smaller sets.
    - Hyakunō Yoin [One hundred stories gathered and their reverberations] / 百衲餘音, undated (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_20)
      The first 15 pages list ointments, their method of manufacture, and their usage and toxicity. The rest of the pages comprise a collection of Dr. Nanhō's case studies of his medical experiences at the inn in Bizen Okayama. Includes the names of the patients, ages, diagnoses, and/or descriptions of symptoms. Also gives a record of medical treatments and medicines. One section is on an obstetric technique to extract a baby using the hands. No date or name of author is given.
    - Hyakunō Yoin / 百衲餘音, undated (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_21)
      A table of contents describes four sections. No name or date is given.
      Section 1: Gan Shōsai hippō: pharmaceutical receipts with dosage instructions. Includes a few illustrations of cauterization.
      Section 2: Dr. Kagawa Yūsai hōkan: gynecological medications.
      Section 3: Dr. Ogi Daishū, fukushin hen: how to examine an abdomen by touch. Written in Sino-Japanese style. Includes corrections and annotations in red ink.
      Section 4: Ban ran yakumeiki: list of names of medicinal herbs in Dutch and Japanese.
    - Hyakunō Yoin Sanka no bu [Obstetrics and gynecology] / 百衲餘音 産科之部, undated (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_22)
      Arranged in four sections, some of which have their own table of contents. No name or date is given.
      Section 1: Kaisei Kōhō hiketsu: Dr. Oku Ressai's oral instruction.
      Section 2: Furoku chiken: appendix, clinical trial; Dr. Oku Ressai's oral lecture.
      Section 3: Kitai zu: illustrations of deformed newborns and embryos from an eight-month pregnancy.
      Section 4: Gekkei hi oakuron: menstruation
      Section 5: Tsuwari setsu: morning sickness
      Section 6: Shikan setsu: eclampsia
      Section 7: Jutai setsu: conception
      Section 8: Danjo setsu: what makes the gender of a baby
      Oku Ressai (奥劣斎) (1780-1835) was an obstetrician in Edo period. He was known for his resuscitation of newborn babies and for the "internal podalic" maneuver of inserting a hand into the uterus and drawing the baby foot-first through the cervix.
    - Hyakunō Yoin Sanka no bu [Obstetrics and gynecology] / 百衲餘音 産科之部, 1822 (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_23)
      Notebook is divided into three sections, all lectures given by physician Oku Ressai but recorded by different students. A title in the text appearing at the bottom of the notebook indicates that this notebook was bound once before, but re-bound later, at which time the first and second halves were mistakenly switched. The characters thus are divided in half, with the bottom half of the characters appearing on top and vice versa.
      Section 1: Sanka shujutsu hiroku [Gynecological operation]: relates to surgeries. Recorded by pupil: Ogata Korekatsu (緒方惟勝). Written in Bunsei Mizunoe uma (Bunsei 5 or 1822) by Kosui.
      Sections 2 and 3: Sanjutsu kaiyō Ken no maki (part 1) and Kon no maki (part 2). Part 1 lists 21 techniques before parturition. Part 2 lists 21 techniques after parturition. They are bound together as Sections 2 and 3. A note says that the two parts were examined by Dr. Ressai and recorded by Nishimura Toku.
      Ogata Korekatsu (緒方惟勝) (1787-1840) was a physician of the Okayama feudal domain; he was known for specializing in internal diseases and obstetrics.
    - Hyakunō Yoin / 百衲餘音, 1829 (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_24)
      Section 1: Suishu [Edema] kagen. Written by Komatsu Hisayasu (小松久安) from Naniwa(Nagoya area).
      Section 2: Kan Shōsai jōyōzai [Kan Shōsai's regularly used medicines]. Copied 1829 April by Shūhin at Saibidō [sakura?] juku /櫻塾.
      Section 3: Keishō. At the end of this section there is an explanation that this was a fictional case study with Dr. Morita Shuichirō; the students discussed the treatment.
      Section 4: Kyō Insai Seikotsu yōketsu. Dr Kyō Insai's osteopathy by Yoshiwara Gentō Ryūsen (吉原元棟隆僊). Has a table of contents on page 35. 1829 March, recorded by Shūhin, half of it at Nanki juku, and other half at Kyōshi juku.
      Morita Shuichirō or Morita Yoshiaki (森田義章) was a doctor in Kyōto who studied under Kawagoe Kōzan.
    - Sanka Hōkaku, [Gynecological methods] / 産科方轂, 1825 (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_25)
      This notebook has two sections; the second is marked with blue corners. Divisions within each section are marked by brown page marks and the subtitles within the section are marked with a red triangle above the writing.
      Section 1: Tasseien Hōkaku. First page has a table of contents with seven topics and a preface after the table of contents. There are two students' names: Kaga Shibahara Junshikei and Bichū Yamanari ___shikyō. There are many corrections in red ink. This section is undated.
      Section 2: Sesseidō Hōkaku. Refers to treatments for difficult gynecological problems, and gives details on medications and drugs. The preface gives the date and author: "Bunsei kinoto tori Aki 7 gatsu [1825] by Tsutsui Bunkei (筒井文敬).
      Sesseido is the gō ("art name"), or alias, of Ogata Korekatsu.
    - Sanka sagen / 産科瑣言, 1828 (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_26)